Summary.

For my PhD, I plan to specialize in the application and theoretical exploration of advanced computational tools such as quantum Monte Carlo, tensor networks, and machine learning, with a focus on their applications in quantum computing, condensed matter physics and AMO. My research is driven by a keen interest in understanding and innovating within these domains, aiming to bridge the gap between theoretical frameworks and practical applications in complex physical systems.

Education.

University of British Columbia

Vancouver, Canada

MS PHYSICS UNDER PROF. ROMAN KREMS

2021 - August 2024

- CGPA: 3.65/4
- Teaching Assistant for PHYS 100 (Classical Mechanics) and PHYS 131 (Electromagnetism)

Delhi Technological University

New Delhi, India

BACHELOR OF TECHNOLOGY IN ENGINEERING PHYSICS

2017 - 2021

CGPA: 8.94/10

St. Xavier's Senior Secondary School

New Delhi, India

GRADE 12 (SENIOR SECONDARY LEVEL)

2017

· Percentage: 89.2%

Publications and Posters

Extrapolation of polaron properties to low phonon frequencies by multi-fidelity Bayesian machine learning

Vancouver, Canada

CONFERENCE TALK/JOURNAL SUBMISSION

August, 2023

- The talk and the poster were presented at RTGdyn Conference (UBC, Freiburg). The slides for the event can be found here (Slides).
- The preprint is available by end of December 2023. To be submitted to Physics Review B

Equivalence between Barren plateaus and kernel concentration problem

Vancouver, Canada

MANUSCRIPT UNDER PREPARATION

August, 2023

- Demonstrated how the training bounds for Barren Plateaus, in quantum neural networks can be transferred to solve the Exponential Concentration problem in quantum kernels and vice versa.
- Proved that symmetry encoded quantum kernels suffer from lower rates of exponential concentration, using concepts from Weingarten Calculus and Lie algebra
- The preprint is available by January 2024

Coherence-based inequality for the discrimination of three-qubit GHZ and W class

JOURNAL ARTICLE January, 2022

 Kairon, P., Singh, M., Adhikari, S. Coherence-based inequality for the discrimination of three-qubit GHZ and W class. Quantum Inf Process 21, 173 (2022) (Link)

Noisy three-player dilemma game: robustness of the quantum advantage

JOURNAL ARTICLE April, 2020

• Kairon, P., Thapliyal, K., Srikanth, R. et al. Noisy three-player dilemma game: robustness of the quantum advantage. Quantum Inf Process 19, 327 (2020) (Link)

COVID-19 Outbreak Prediction Using Quantum Neural Networks

DoSIER 2020 (Virtual)

CONFERENCE PAPER

June, 2021

• Kairon, P., Bhattacharyya, S. (2021). COVID-19 Outbreak Prediction Using Quantum Neural Networks. In: Bhattacharyya, S., Dutta, P., Datta, K. (eds) Intelligence Enabled Research. Advances in Intelligent Systems and Computing, vol 1279. Springer, Singapore (Link)

Simulation of 2019-nCoV envelope formation as a platform for screening therapeutics which may interfere with viral protein-protein interactions

Abstract presented at International Conference on Complex Systems, 2020

May, 2020

• The abstract is available at (Link)

Experimental test of quantum advantage 3- player noisy dilemma game

Munich, Germany (Virtual)

POSTER PRESENTED AT MCQST

July, 2020

1

• The poster is available at (Link)

PRANAV KAIRON · RÉSUMÉ

Thesis Projects

Bayesian extrapolation of quantum observables in Hamiltonian parameter spaces

UBC, Canada

GRADUATE RESEARCH PROJECT AT UBC

• I used Gaussian process regression with kernel selection algorithm to extrapolate polaron dispersion relations in hamiltonian parameter space such as phonon frequency, momentum, and coupling. Using Green's function cluster expansion for data acquisition in the adiabatic regime, the model accurately predicted phase transitions at lower phonon frequencies and explored the extreme adiabatic regime of Peierls polaron physics, addressing challenges in high-temperature superconductivity research.

Equivalence between Barren plateaus and kernel concentration problem

UBC, Canada

GRADUATE RESEARCH PROJECT AT UBC

- Derived conditional relations that can transfer the bounds derived for Barren plateaus in quantum neural networks to quantum kernels.
- · Dervied strict lower bounds for covariant quantum kernels, and showed how they can avoid exponential concentration

Additional unpublished projects

UBC, Canada

GRADUATE RESEARCH PROJECT AT UBC

- Worked on designing an experimental proposal using quantum dot based analogue simulator for simulating attosecond physics in atoms, specifically HHG spectra in 1D hydrogen atom. I used tools like COMSOL (to desing quantum dots), PETSc (large scale parallel simulation)
- Applied ML to predict **the topological phase transition and Dirac Cones in twisted multilayer cuprates** by training Gaussian process model with data from trivial phase. Further extended it to predict Conical Intersections in CH₂NH potential energy surface.
- Writing my own **DMRG code** for electron-phonon models based on pseudo-site method.

Coherence based inequality for state discrimination

DTU, India

BACHELOR'S THESIS UNDER DR. SATYABRAT ADHIKARI AND DR. MUKHTIYAAR SINGH

- · Studied the relationship between coherence and entanglement measures in discrete/continuous quantum systems.
- Developed coherence based inequality for the classification of GHZ class and W class of three-qubit states.
- · Extended it further to possible implementation of the scheme in an experiment, to reduce the number of projective measurements.

Experience_

Mitacs Accelerate Canada

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP October, 2023 - August, 2024

- Using quantum machine learning methods to perform feature selection for a biomedical dataset with millions of dimensions.
- Wrote a grant proposal in collaboration with my supervisor and the company for 30k CAD.

Superconducting Circuit Design and Fabrication

Canada

RESEARCH WORKSHOP BY CMC MICROSYSTEMS

June, 2022 - July, 2022

- Gained hands-on experience in designing, simulating, and fabricating superconducting circuits, including resonators, SQUIDs, and qubits, utilizing CMC-provided CAD tools.
- Conducted advanced testing of superconducting chips using a 4K probe station and a dilution refrigerator, demonstrating proficiency in low-temperature experimental techniques crucial for quantum information science. Participated in the Quantum Fab Lab at Institut quantique, enhancing skills in the practical application of quantum devices and experimental setup.

HCL Technologies Bengaluru, India

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP

August, 2021 - September, 2021

- $\bullet \ \ \text{Benchmarked various methods present for solving electronic structure problem on DWave quantum annealer (AWS Amazon Braket).}$
- Presented a report on error mitigation schemes for variational quantum eigensolver, where error is mitigated by exploiting the symmetries in Hamiltonian.

Conduit Computing Boston, USA (Remote)

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP

March, 2020 - January, 2021

- Worked on drug development for Covid-19 by simulating proteins using NAMD and VMD with help of Fronterra supercomputer.
- Project selected for White House HPC consortium and Nvidia Supercomputers.
- Literature survey for using Quantum tensor network methods to perform Quantum Monte Carlo simulations for applications to risk analysis.
- Full research proposal presented at Quantum British Columbia, Virtual Poster Presentation on quantum computing.

Qnu Labs {India's first Quantum Company}

Bengaluru, India

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP UNDER DR. ANINDITA BANERJEE

December, 2019 - January, 2020

- Worked on discrete phase randomization of Differential Phase shift QKD and COW protocol.
- Developed MATLAB/Mathematica programs to calculate key rate deterioration with distance for various DPS protocols.
- Developing reports on high throughput Quantum random number generators which can be simulated experimentally in the lab, that rely
 on random generation using phase noise of LASER.

PRANAV KAIRON · RÉSUMÉ

2

Solid State Physics Laboratory - DRDO

Delhi, India

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP May, 2019 - August, 2019

 Worked on characterizing Gold, HOPG, MCT, GaAs samples using Scanning Tunnelling Microscopy and Electrical characterization AlN thin films on Si(111) by fabricating MIS structures.

Renewed a broken 40K \$ worth of table top STM and configured the software re-installation and hardware setup by myself.

Solid State Physics Laboratory - DRDO

Delhi, India

Dec, 2018 - February, 2019

- MATLAB modelling of Thin film characterization using X-ray reflectivity.
- Composition, Stress & Strain determination of AlGaN/GaN multilayer for HEMT devices

Laser Science and Technology Center - DRDO

Delhi, India

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP

May, 2018 - August, 2021

- Worked on development of optical resonator for high power Lasers using Nd-doped PoCl3 as the gain medium Developed MATLAB program for the same.
- Surveyed various optical coatings for laser grade mirrors.

Honours, Grants & Scholarships

- Mitacs Accelerate Grant, Obtained a grant for a 10 month internship in collaboration with 2023 Biomedical startup to find usecases quantum machine learning on their dataset
- **IBM Error correction summer school**, Selected for in person IBM summer school in New York, 2022 out of hundreds of applicants
- Commendable Research Award at DTU, Won the commendable research award and a cash 2022 prize of Rs. 50k for publishing a journal article as part of my bachelor's thesis.
- Quantum BC Roadmapping Workshop, Won first place in Roadmapping workshop, Developed 2022 quantum based solution for an industrially relevant genomics problem
- Quest Fellowship, Stewart Blusson Quantum Matter Institute, University of British 2021 Columbia, Canada
- NSERC Quantum Computing CREATE Scholarship, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, 2021 Canada
- MCQST Summer School 2021, Shortlisted among 20 students among 500 applicants all over 2021 the world for first Munich Center of Quantum Science and Technology Summer School Cornerstone Models of Quantum Computing online summer school, Selected for summer school
- conducted by Quantum British Columbia among 130 undergraduate & graduate 2020 candidates
- 2017 All India Rank - 4922, JEE Main, taken by approximately 1.5 million students.

Skills

Programming Languages Python, C++, MATLAB, Mathematica

Utilities Git/Github, Linux Shell, VScode, Jupyter

Extracurricular Activity

NSERC Quantum Computing, CREATE

Vancouver, Canada

MENTOR AND JUDGE AT HIGH SCHOOL ENGINEERING AND DESIGN COMPETITION

November 2022

 Mentored two groups of five high school students each. Students were supposed to show how can quantum computing be used in interplanetary communication. Later we judged the final presentations

Deltech Engineering Physics Technological Hub, Delhi Technological University

Delhi, India 2017 - 2021

VICE-PRESIDENT, LECTURER FOR THE TERM 2020-21

- DEPTH is an undergraduate society which organizes seminars, debates, guest lectures, paper presentations intended at enhancement in knowledge of and unfolding of various scientific fields before its members.
- Conducted lectures on various topics not covered in university courses.
- Mentored beginners in the field to explore the various topics systematically.

Student Mentorship Programme

Delhi, India 2019 - 2021

- Personally mentored five freshmen from the Engineering Physics Department.
- Individually guided them through personal and academic problems for the entire year.

PRANAV KAIRON · RÉSUMÉ